Right, so today is going to be our first, I believe,
of two problem sessions covering dynamic programming.
I
find dynamic programming is one of these interesting parts of an
algorithms class where, somehow, the people that are really good at it are
completely disjoint with the people that are good
at all the other parts of the algorithms class.
So for some of you guys,
that might be promising.
And for others, maybe
a little bit less so.
So maybe we'll spend just a minute or two kind of reviewing the basic ideas
we're going to apply in these problems because they all follow more or
less the same template. Although, of course,
as usual in 6 .006, we like to put some
interesting window dressing around it so that
it's not totally obvious what you're doing.
And then we'll do a
bunch of sample problems.
Right, so let's talk a little bit about
dynamic programming and the basic idea here.
So dynamic programming is kind of a funny outlier in 6 .006 in that,
for example, in the data structures part of the course, we learned what?
No, I'm struggling to
think of a data structure.
Like useful trees and arrays or whatever. And these are
actually things that you can code. If you look in C++,
there are, well, plausibly, it could be an
implementation of a tree. And there's some way.
And so these are useful algorithms that you could maybe even read the
pseudocode. And there's a universe where you really do translate that
pseudocode into something
inside of your laptop.
Dynamic programming is a little bit less so. This is more of like a meta.
I don't know if you call it a meta algorithm or a problem solving approach
or what.
But it's not like you somehow say, I'm going to apply the dynamic programming
algorithm to this problem. But rather, it's sort of this big class of
things that all follow a similar template or sort of approach to things.
And so I think that's kind of what I was thinking about problem solving,
which I think sort of explains
why, actually, in some sense,
the last couple lectures that you've seen, and I guess if I'm getting the
time sequence of our course right, the next couple ones that you will see.
And the problem sessions actually start to coincide in the
sense that when Eric was teaching you guys dynamic programming,
how did he do it? Well, he didn't write down, well, he sort of wrote down
some template for dynamic programming. But then we just did a bunch of
sample problems.
And that's exactly what
we're going to do today.
All of these things are just going to converge in this part of our course
because dynamic programming, it's really more of a way of life than any
particular algorithm.
And this is a pattern that I think
you see a lot in advanced algorithms.
Like, for example, in my
universe, numerical analysis,
when
you talk about the ADMM algorithm, it's actually a totally useless
algorithm. What matters is applying it to a particular problem.
And this is sort of, I think, a more mature or grown
up way to think about a lot of things in algorithms.
And this sort of general purpose stuff that's useful all the time, I
think, starts to disperse a little bit in favor of different patterns and
mechanisms that you're used to thinking about. So there's my 10
seconds sort of philosophical introduction to what we're doing,
during which I've managed to
chase this table across the room.
You know, I played, I did college on the West Coast. And I thought I was
going to be a music major. And there was a piano master class where we
forgot to put the little
clips on the wheels.
And I just thought I was really nervous because
the piano was literally slipping away from me.
And I can never think of that
Chopin nocturne quite the same way.
But in any event,
in dynamic programming,
Eric laid out for you guys a particular sort of set of steps that are sort
of a useful problem solving approach in the dynamic programming universe.
In today's problem session, I'm going to try
and help you guys translate a little bit from
this template to what it means to actually write code to implement a dynamic
programming algorithm because I think it's a little easy to forget that
here.
But on the other hand, on your homework, when you're writing out answers
to algorithms problems, it's perfectly fine to follow this template, even
letter, I guess,
literally letter for letter,
and answer each of these questions.
And then sort of the remaining
glue that you need to actually write the code is not
terribly exciting from an algorithms theory perspective.
So the basic idea here is that this is a lot of different
problems that can be written recursively in some sense.
Certainly, we've
encountered many of those in this course. In fact, I think the bias in the
way that we've presented algorithms that don't have to be recursive is to
write them in a recursive way.
And the point here is that when you have
a recursive call and you repeat something,
you give the function the
same input more than one time,
you might as well remember what you
got the last time you saw that input.
And then you don't have to
do that computation again.
So in this sentence, I think that's roughly the
logic behind all these dynamic programming things.
So there's no reason to be
too redundant with lecture.
For just sort of the
10 -second overview,
I think that there's an example which is simultaneously
good and misleading, which is this Fibonacci sequence.
It's good in the sense that the logic of dynamic programming is really
easy. It's bad in that the runtime is kind of weird to think about.
But remember that your Fibonacci
sequence looks something like f of k equals
f of k minus 1
plus f of k minus 2.
And if you look at your sort of recursive call
tree here, like let's say that I do k equals 4,
then it's going to call
my function f is going to have to evaluate it at 3 and 2.
And then the 3 is going to evaluate it 2 and 1 and so on.
And the thing to notice
is that when I call f of 4,
or rather f of 3 here,
if there were 3 somewhere else
in my tree, I get the same number.
So in particular,
f of 2 and f of 2,
both of these are going to take some amount of algorithmic work. But if
just the first time I see a 2, I have a little piece of scratch paper and I
say, ah, any time I see k equals 2, just return
this number rather than doing recursive calls,
then in effect, if there's any
subtree underneath this thing,
I've just pruned
it from my tree.
And so that's the
basic logic here.
And that's basically the
paradigm that's going on in this
sort bot acronym,
which is you first take your
problem and divide it into subproblems.
That is mysterious.
Why is this board moving?
Oh, there's a phone in my
pocket. I bumped against the wall.
I'm not used to this classroom.
Right.
Yeah, so the first thing I want to do is to write my problem as sort of
this sort of form. Notice that we've done this a lot in this class. We've
written things recursively. The difference here is that the sort of
argument that goes into recursion is typically maybe a little simpler than
putting some giant data structure
inside of there or something like that.
So for instance, merge sort, you could write in this paradigm. I guess we
covered that. But it's probably not the most natural way to think about
merge sort.
Then we need to relate our subproblems to each other. So for instance, in
the Fibonacci sequence problem, I just gave you the relation that sort of
what defines the problem.
Incidentally, this is what
a model for the reproduction of rabbits, I think, if I
remember reading the history of the Fibonacci sequence.
And then I think to me the most, not necessarily unnatural, but I think
the thing that maybe is hardest to translate to an algorithm if you're
thinking about writing code is
this idea of topological order.
The basic idea here is that like, if f of 1
depended on f of 2 and f of 2 depended on f of 1,
I'd be in a lot of trouble because somehow my tree would never
converge, for one thing, if I made these recursive calls.
And I'd never be able to memoize or
kind of remember a value when I move on.
And so the idea here is that there's some ordering
of my subproblems so that I can build up a solution.
And there's sort of two dual ways
to think about why that's useful.
So in the memoization
universe, what do I do?
I can write a statement saying, if
I've already evaluated f of k, return it.
That's perfectly fine.
The other thing I can do is if I write
my subproblems in topological order,
then I can sort of go in the reverse direction and
build up my memoization table. So for instance,
for the Fibonacci sequence problem, I could do f
of 1 and then f of 2 and then f of 3 and f of 4
all the way until I get to the k value that I actually wanted. And
those are just duals of the same coin, exactly the same approach of the
memoization version. Sometimes you can prune out some problems that you
didn't actually need to solve. So for instance, maybe this was f of k minus
7.
And so I can skip a
few indices in my array.
I don't think typically that has a big effect on runtime for the problems
that we've seen, but it could plausibly in some universe. So I'd have to
think about a problem where
that makes a difference.
Right, and then I think the bot part of
sort bot is a little easier to think about.
Recursion has a base case, like
when is this thing going to stop?
That's exactly the same as
just any recursive algorithm.
The O for original, I think, is a little bit retrofit to make sort bot
sound nice. But I think the idea here is that you need to go back to your
original problem and make sure that it corresponds to one of the
function calls that you've written and all this complicated stuff.
Hopefully, that's a reasonable characterization.
And then finally, the T is more, these are for
describing your
algorithm. For analyzing it.
And again, the bot part of sort bot almost applies to anything
we've done in 6 .006. You should always analyze your runtime.
OK, so in any event, that's my 10 -minute
version of the last couple lectures.
And I think more or less enough to get
us started with some sample problems here.
Sorry, I couldn't help
it. I like to teach things.
OK, so right. So in our problem session, we have a few
of the homework problems from last year to go over.
Tim is MIT backwards, so he
happens to fit into this goofy
game that Jason likes to play in
writing homework problems anyway.
But it's also the MIT mascot.
Anyway, I got very excited.
Right, so what's going
on in this problem?
So Tim the Beaver has kind
of an interesting mathematics.
I think you would call this a martingale if you flip
the coin a little bit when you solve this problem.
But luckily, Tim the Beaver is
a deterministic kind of a guy.
And he looks at
the weather outside.
And if it's a temperature T, apparently,
Tim the Beaver is OK with boiling.
The higher the temperature, the happier Tim gets.
So this is a first derivative kind of a phenomenon.
In particular, on a given
day, if I have a temperature T,
Tim the Beaver has two things
that he can do to change his mood.
Apparently, Tim the Beaver's mood never
stays fixed. It always goes up and down.
In particular,
he can either go outside,
in which
case the happiness
increases by T.
Or he can stay inside,
in which case his happiness
decreases
by T.
OK, so every day,
Tim the Beaver,
he wakes up. I really want to say that he checks
for his shadow. But that's a gopher, right?
In any event, he wakes up in the morning. He checks the weather. And he
makes a determination, does he want to go outside or not? And if he goes
outside, he gets happier by an
amount that's equal to the temperature.
If he stays inside, he gets less happy by an amount that's equal to
the temperature. By the way, I think our solution is perfectly fine if
temperatures are negative
here, in which case,
I guess everything would
kind of flip intuitively.
But there's no reason to
get too hung up on that.
But of course,
there's a twist here.
So Tim,
as with many of you,
has n days
until his final exam.
So in particular,
he never wants to go.
He's come up with a personal resolve to
never go outside more than two days in a row.
And
so
the question is, because that way, he has to stay inside
and study at least one out of every three -ish days.
OK,
so the question is, how can
Tim maximize his happiness?
Incidentally,
in machine learning, sometimes they call that minimizing regret, which I
always found to be a very sad way to think about algorithms when there's a
totally dual version. But Tim's an optimistic guy. He wants to maximize his
happiness, subject to this constraint that he cannot go outside more than
two days in a row.
So if I go out on
Monday and Tuesday,
I'll go out on Wednesday.
Yes? I think there's no effect to his happiness when he stays
in. There's no effect to his happiness when he stays in.
At least that's . No, it says with a
decrease in happiness when t is negative.
That's not actually going
to affect our problem at all.
It's not going to affect it.
Sure, yeah, I can fix this life.
I can do the problem myself before looking at
the answer and then don't check it closely.
Fine, so let's change that.
I like this problem better somehow
psychologically, but that's OK.
Right, so Jason correctly points out that if you actually
read the problem, what's asked there is slightly different,
that when he goes outside, his happiness increases
by t. If he stays inside, his happiness does nothing.
So it stays the same.
My apologies.
So Tim the beaver is a particularly optimistic beaver. His happiness
can only increase in time, assuming he lives in a climate with positive
temperatures.
OK, now I think I've
got it right now.
Cool, let's see if
I can still do this.
Yeah, I think basically
nothing changes.
OK, that's great.
All right, I'm going to do it.
OK,
so right, so the question is,
how do we solve this problem?
And thankfully, I think we put the easiest problem
first. And in particular, if we're following our sort by
paradigm here, somehow there's a set of subproblems that
are staring us in the face. That's the word I'm looking for.
In particular,
well, there's only one index in
our problem, which is what day it is.
So the obvious thing to do would be to say, can we figure out the maximum
amount of happiness for days, say, i to the last day? By the way, if I do
that, I'm using the prefix
version of my problem.
Suffix version of my problem. I could also do it
the opposite way and work from the end back in.
Maybe if we have time all the way to the end, we'll
do the second one. But it doesn't really matter.
OK,
so in particular,
just to add a little
bit of notation,
let's say that
t of i is equal
to the temperature
on day i.
And now we're going to make a new thing, which is
going to be the actual variable we want to compute.
This is going to be x of i,
which we'll write is the
maximum happiness
that you can achieve if you only
consider the calendar from day i
to day n.
I guess inclusive.
Incidentally, just for convenience, we'll assume that
xi is equal to 0 if I go past the end of my array.
So I think it's kind of a typical
thing to do in these DP algorithms.
OK, so the question is, can we actually come up with
a recursive algorithm that computes xi using this nice
sort of topologically acyclic way of thinking about our
problem? The answer is obviously yes. I wouldn't be here today.
And so in the absence of a smarter idea, let's just
do the Toucan -Sam approach here and follow our nose
and see if we can just write
our problem in terms of other ones.
So in general, let's say that
Tim the Beaver wakes up on day i.
He has basically two decisions that
he can make. He can either stay inside
or he can not stay
inside. He can go outside.
So let's just basically
handle these three cases.
So in case one,
he stays inside.
Well, now what happens
to his happiness?
Well,
according to my revised
version of this problem, nothing.
So in particular,
what do we know?
If he stays inside, then he has any decision he can make
tomorrow. It doesn't matter. He can go inside. He can go outside,
whatever, because by having stayed inside, he's earned
himself two free days of going outside if he wants.
So in particular, in this case,
we can convince ourselves that
this is true in our,
I think,
yes.
So in other words, while he gives no utility for today, he
wakes up tomorrow and he can make whatever decision he wants.
OK.
The second thing
he can do is go out.
This is where things
get a little tricky.
Can I just do like take ti and
add it to xi plus 1? What goes wrong?
Maybe
you go out three days in a row.
You somehow have to remember that.
And so that's where things
are a little bit of a headache.
In particular, if I go out today and
tomorrow, I can't go out the day after that.
And somehow, if we just dealt with this one case as ti plus
xi plus 1, we wouldn't remember that. And that's a problem.
So instead, what we can do is
think of there being two subcases.
So what we're going to assume is that not only does he
go out today, but that he's free to go out tomorrow.
That's a massive assumption
as we move down our array.
So if we do that,
well, now we have
case A and case B.
So in case A,
he goes out today and
he stays in tomorrow.
OK.
So what happens
in this case? Well,
by
the way, I'm using this kind of weird arrow notation. I don't know if this
is good or not. But essentially, the point is that I'm keeping track of
cases.
And then eventually, I'm going to want to
have to take the max over all of these things.
So I don't like the equal sign because
somehow that's a little misleading.
Right. So in that case, while he gets
the utility of having gone out today,
tomorrow he stays in,
which means that the day after tomorrow, he can do whatever
the heck he wants. He has free reign. So I can write that.
Using this recursive call.
Similarly,
right.
So I'm getting the hang of this.
Sorry.
This is way too entertaining for
me. I can play with this board all day.
OK. So in case 2B, he goes out
today and he goes out tomorrow.
OK.
So
he's a party animal.
He is an animal and he's going out a
lot. Right. So in that case, what happens?
Well, he gets that.
He gets today's utility.
He gets tomorrow's utility.
The day after, he has to stay
in. So we might as well skip it.
And then he can do
whatever he wants.
The day after that.
OK.
So
if we go back, I
guess technically,
we should revise our definition of x a tiny bit. That is not the maximum
happiness. Well, we can convince ourselves that it's the same thing. But
really, it's not the maximum
happiness for day i through n.
It's the maximum happiness for day i through n under the
assumption that he has permission to go out on day i.
Right. And that's really what's going
on in our recursive set of calls here.
OK.
Does our recursion
make sense here?
All right.
So
let's see here. So if we're following our sort bot, I keep reviewing
papers that use the word paradigm a lot. So I feel like I should do that.
So
what is t? It's the
topological order.
Notice that xi only depends
on larger i's.
So in terms of our topological order, the
dependence graph is really simple. It's just a line.
So
remember that you can think about topological order, or you can think
about being acyclic graph. Those are equivalent. We covered that in this
course. I kind of like
thinking about acyclic graph.
So x1 depends on x2, depends on x3, depends on
x4. That graph has no cycles. So we're good.
So next, we have to come up with
our base case for our recursion.
Notice that the
way I have chosen
to solve this problem is
by calling future indices,
which means that my base case sits at the end of my array. Because that's
sort of like the lowest down on the recursion chain is what I'm going for.
But I kind of like the
recursion train better.
In particular,
on day n,
well, if he has permission
to go out on day n,
he can do one of two things. He can
either go out or not. It doesn't matter.
Right. So in particular,
we can say that that's
the max
of 0 or t of n.
Remember, I didn't tell you that
temperatures have to be positive.
Maybe he's a Celsius
kind of a beaver.
OK.
And then in addition to that,
for convenience, notice that there's a universe where I
look beyond the end of my array in my recursive call here.
So I should probably
think about a few extra x's.
Obviously, the utility of going
out a day that doesn't exist is 0.
So we can say that xn plus
1 equals xn plus 2 equals 0.
OK.
I've managed to use way too much
space for one simple algorithmic problem.
Oh, boy.
OK.
So.
Yeah?
Can I get credit for that? OK.
Right. So now we need to do the O and
the t. So what's our original problem?
Well, remember that he wants to
maximize his happiness starting on day 1.
So our original
problem is just x of 1.
Or is it?
So remember that Tim the beaver, this is, you know, your instructor is very
sloppy when it comes to actually reading the problems, as you saw at the
beginning.
And the mistake for which I would have personally lost points where I do
solve this problem on my homework is that it didn't ask for just the maximum
amount of happiness
that Tim could achieve.
That's not very practical
for your everyday beaver.
But rather, he wants to know the actual plan. He wants
to know what days he can go out and what days he can't.
Yeah?
And I haven't actually told you how to do that. Right? I've only told
you how to compute x, which is just the maximum amount of happiness.
what's happening between types.
And it would be interesting
to use Win environment solvable
And now I can reconstruct my plan very
easily. So I look at x1. If I took option 1,
then I stay in and
I look at day 2.
If I took option 2a,
then I can label today,
tomorrow,
and the day after. Wait.
Yeah, that's right. I
can label today's choice,
tomorrow's choice, the days after
choice, and then look three days later
and recurse that way.
Or option b is kind of similar.
So a reasonable way to
reconstruct the actual set
of what days you go out and what days you go in is just
to remember as you do your memorization or whatever,
whether you did option 1, 2a, or 2b. And then it's pretty easy to
reconstruct from there. Maybe I'll let you guys convince yourselves of
that at home or in the last eight seconds if you
happen to be the two audience members that I have.
And then finally, we need to do our time thing. And most of the time
arguments here follow more or less the same pattern, which is you count the
number of subproblems and the time per subproblem. You multiply those
two things together, and you get your runtime. We're going to see in one
problem on this problem set that's not quite right
because we have to account for some precomputation.
But in this case, it is.
Right.
So let's see. What are
our subproblems here?
Well, essentially, I guess I didn't actually say it,
but you have to take the max of these three values.
Max of three expressions, which have a constant number of
plus signs and lookups and memory and all that good stuff.
So each subproblem takes
order one time.
How many subproblems are there?
Well, there's, I guess, n plus
2 max if you want to be conservative about it.
So in particular, there's order n subproblems.
So all I have to do is multiply these two things
together, and my algorithm takes order n time.
And that's our solution
to problem number one.
Any questions so far?
Yes. Uh -oh.
When I was thinking about the problem beforehand,
I was wondering, could you use base cases?
Right now, we have two
different kinds of base case,
a base case for x of n and
a base case for things after.
Could I remove the first one? And add an x of
n plus 3 equals 0 as well? What would that do?
Could I remove the first
one and add an x of n plus 3?
Yeah, I guess that's fine.
I'm sorry. That's not a particularly helpful
answer for the people watching on video.
My answer to this question
you can't hear is yes.
Right. So the
question, to repeat,
was
this base case is somehow
kind of complicated looking.
To be fair, it's the one that
I always think given assignment.
But that's OK.
But the question is,
is this truly necessary?
In particular, can I get rid of the xn case and instead add
a third day past the end of time, which also has value 0?
And if you kind of
look at that plus case b,
I think you could,
or rather case a, I think you could convince you, well, case a and b
for that matter, you could convince yourself that these are equivalent.
That's absolutely right. So I could add
a third day after the end of this thing,
which also has value 0.
Or by the way, I could just
say in my code,
if i is bigger than n, return
0. That's the same thing.
Yeah, and then I guess I don't have to worry
about that xn case. Yeah, these are the same.
To each their own.
Fabulous question. Any others
that I can answer while we're at it?
Cool.
All right, so
that's problem one.
I'm writing too big. I
don't like this big chalk.
OK, so problem two is the one that got me all hot and bothered yesterday.
So let's see if we do any better in front of people, because that's usually
the best way to improve
problem solving skill.
Right,
so in problem two, which annoyingly is also probably the most practical
problem on this problem set, essentially you have a, I suppose I should write
some stuff down. Right,
so in problem, oh, I
used the wrong side,
two,
you have an operating system,
men x,
whatever,
which is a,
apparently it's a very simple.
Oh,
I get it.
Doesn't mean I have to like it.
Right, so in men x,
yeah.
Yeah, apparently the only thing that my operating
system can do is compute edit distance between files.
And it wants to
do so efficiently.
So
we have that a file
is a sequence of strings.
And I believe we
say their length
is less than or equal to k. That's
going to come into play a little bit later.
But basically, it's just
lines of the different files.
So
there's three different ways
that we can change a file.
So here are the
changes we could do.
Change number one
is to add a line.
Change number two
is to remove a line.
And change number three
is to swap.
But a caveat for
this interesting model of what's cheap and what's not is that apparently
swapping two lines is cheap because they exist in memory. Like maybe I'm,
I don't know, using like a linked
list or something to store files.
And so swapping two
pointers isn't so bad.
But inserting and removing a line is hard because,
I don't know, memory allocation is expensive.
Like, you know, me nix is actually
operating on clay. Tablets and
I can chop my clay tablets into different slices and just pick them up and
swap them. And that's fine. But if I want to add a line to my file, I have
to go to the Tigris and Euphrates and pull out the, or whatever
it was, the Eugris and the Typhrates and pull out a stone.
It's a lot of work to make
a new line or to dispose.
So these are expensive.
And this is cheap.
And so the question that
I'm trying to say, that
I'm trying to say and that
the problem is trying to
ask is that you
are given
files
A and
B with n lines each.
You want to know what the minimum
number of non -swap operations it'll take.
And so in other words, the minimum number
of times you need to add and remove lines
to transform A into B,
right?
Essentially with low cost.
And in fact,
just to be nice, I think that's actually
kind of a critical hint in this problem.
We give you the runtime.
And I'm going to kind of ignore it in my answer. And notice that I did
something wrong and then go back and fix it. This is different from the way
the answer is written where God came in and said like, oh, we observe that
we're probably going to need this thing. So we're going to go ahead and do
it here.
I think that's maybe not
representative of the logic here.
So the runtime here
is k n plus n squared.
The first thing to
notice, there is a k here.
And so someday, we're going
to have to compare strings.
Because that's what k is.
And I think that's sort of the hint that's
implicit in this problem. It's easy to miss.
And so indeed, what we're going to notice is we're going
to look at our solution and say, well, wait a second. If we
didn't incur a factor of k, we
must have done something wrong.
And indeed, that's
going to be the case. But
it's only a minor fix to change it. There's
another important distinction on swaps.
Oh, I'm sorry. Yeah. And right, when I
swap things, they have to be adjacent.
I can't write at the
bottom of the board.
That's supposed to be A, D,
J for those watching at home.
But you can only swap
lines that are adjacent
as they appear in
their original file.
I'll say it out loud rather than try and write it because
it's going to take the rest of the lecture to do that.
OK.
Any other things I've forgotten?
This is high likelihood
I'm bad at this.
OK. So
this one was annoying.
Actually, annoying is actually a relatively easy instance of a very well
-known dynamic program plus a tiny bit of additional stuff, which is called
edit distance.
In fact, I think if you guys are
looking for intuition on this problem,
you might Google that
one first as sort of a,
what was that?
Oh, in fact, you're doing a recitation. Oh, that's why. It's not
totally unreasonable to come up with the answer here. Even better.
But even if you hadn't, this is just another dynamic
programming problem. That's just like a little bit more.
Annoying than your average
dynamic programming problem.
Now, the solution written out
in the course notes works from
sort of the last line of the
file downward in some sense.
Upward?
Whatever.
I literally lost two hours of my life trying to think about editing files
from the end up and just getting myself all upset and confused. So here,
I'm going to attempt to do it in the other direction and
probably introduce a bunch of mistakes in the process.
So what
do we do in dynamic programming if we don't know
what else to do? We do sort stuff, sort bot.
And so let's do that here.
So in particular,
what are our subproblems?
This is a little bit funky.
Actually, even before we do the S of sort,
let's think about our problem a little bit.
Let's think about what
it actually means to edit a
file because this is what helped me think about the right answer
here. Which is to say, so what's going on? I have two documents.
This is document A.
This is document B.
Each one of them is
composed of a bunch of lines.
And I'm basically trying to turn A into B. And
the only thing I can do is scribble out a line,
insert, just hit the Enter key, or
do a third thing where I kind of swap
two things that are adjacent to one
another. This is the only thing I can do.
And the way that I like
to think about this problem,
what
I can't jump all over my document because keeping track of that
whole edit history is going to be somehow combinatorially ginormous.
I'm not the track changes
button in Microsoft Word.
I want the minimum
number of changes.
And if I have to recurse over all possible
edits to every single line in any order,
that's an awful lot of factorials and 2 to the n's floating around that I
don't want to have. And so that's the sort of crux of the challenge here,
is to organize my approach
to editing these files in a way that doesn't require me to have to do this
sort of combinatorial jumping all over the place. And I think it's also
the one where the sort of, like I know Jerry Kane at
Stanford talks a lot about the recursive leap of faith.
You know, like somehow dividing your problem into organized
subproblems. That's really where the challenge lives here.
So if
I were a more organized PhD advisor, the way that I
would edit a file or a clay tablet, I guess in this case,
would be linearly. That I might as well do whatever the heck
I'm going to do to line one before I move on to line two.
And at the end of the day, even if I did stuff in a different order, you
can convince yourself that I could always order it in such a way that all
the edits that I do to the first line kind
of happen before lines later in the document.
With the possible
exception of this swap thing.
But we'll see. That
somehow doesn't matter.
And moreover,
if I do an edit, I might as well do the edit to make things better. There's
no reason to just start like willy nilly inserting and removing lines. I
might as well always
do an operation
that improves stuff.
And so thinking about
that sort of logic leads me
to a particular way that
I might write down my s.
My subproblems here, which is to say that I'm going
to think about editing my document line by line.
So in other words, once I've dealt with line one, meaning that I've found
some way to mess with it and make it match line one of the other guy,
I'm just going
to kind of think about removing it and then
thinking about the rest of the document.
You start saying, aha, that
sentence sounds like recursion.
And that's right. That's how
we're going to solve this problem.
So in particular,
here's going to be our thing.
We're going to do a different one in the
solution. So you guys should all be vigilant.
Which is I'm going to write xij
to be the min
work
to convert.
I'm
not a Python programmer, but
hopefully I got this right.
i colon is going to be everything
from i to the end of the file.
So in other words, this is the
suffix version of our problem.
And the into b
j colon.
Like that.
So in other words, I have a
little, it's kind of like a video.
Think about Tetris. Once you get that full line of blocks, you can just
throw that line of blocks away and the whole video game moves down.
There's somehow something very similar going on here, which is the second
I've managed to get a match for line one of document into line one of the
next document.
I'm just going to throw it away and pretend like
I have two documents with one less line in them.
Now, the thing that got
me all hung up last night.
My original problem assumes that both
of my documents have the same length.
But here I'm not
making that assumption.
And essentially, what we're going to figure out
is that actually doesn't matter a whole lot.
If I end up with one
document of length k,
well, I shouldn't use k. One document of
length l and another document of length 0,
what's the amount of work
that I should do to convert?
Well,
l. Because my only choice
is to insert a bunch of lines
in one document,
by the way. Or delete a bunch of lines from the other.
Those are dual to one another. They're exactly the same.
I'm philosophizing a lot because I'm also convincing
myself that my answer is OK in the process.
OK.
So this is going to be our set
of subproblems. And now we have to
do the r.
So the first thing I'm going to do is just do all the
possible edits that I can do to line i and line j.
And that's perfectly fine in this problem. I think the problem is a little
slick and the way that they've written the solution, they've convinced
themselves that some things are equivalent to others and removed them. But
you don't have to. As long as there's a constant number of cases, you're
golden,
pony boy.
In particular, let's
think about some cases.
So first of all,
if line i matches
line j of my document,
remember that it's not really line j. It's like making
a document that just happens to kind of start at line j.
It's like taking scissors.
Well, then I can match
them with zero cost
because the beginnings
are in the same place.
And I can move my
Tetris game down one.
And that's perfectly fine.
So case one, I think, is the
easiest one, which is if a i
equals b j,
then I can just remove that line from both documents and
move forward. In which case, I'll use my same goofy notation.
I'm going to get that x i j.
Well, I'm going to just
increment i and j and keep going,
like that.
Cool?
OK. So
what's something else I could
do? I could delete a line.
So what happens?
OK.
So
case two is delete
a i.
That's a different
thing I can do to line i.
Well, now what do I have to do? I have a document on the left -hand side,
which is one line shorter. And on the right -hand side, nothing changed.
But deleting a line cost me $1.
So in particular, I have
that x i j.
Well, what happens? Well,
I got rid of one line.
But I had to pay.
OK. Let's think about
some other things.
You could delete b j.
This case actually isn't in the solution
because it turns out to be unnecessary.
Well, we're only
allowed to edit a.
Oh, I'm only allowed to edit a? Oh, in
that case, I don't have to delete b j.
I really didn't read these
problems very closely. That's my bad.
This would have made it much easier.
I really should read these things.
Cool. So that eliminates
half of the cases of my notes.
Fabulous.
Incidentally, you could
do these things on the other direction. And it
really wouldn't change this problem a whole lot.
Sorry. I have this bad habit when I'm reading research papers of reading
the research paper I wanted to be there instead of the one that's actually
on the paper.
And somehow, it's a very
similar phenomenon here.
OK. Right.
So great. So I can only edit document a, which makes
this problem way easier than what I was worried about.
Fabulous. In that case,
bananas.
What's our third case here?
Well,
let's see. I could also insert
a line.
Let's see. So what ends up happening
there? So I can only edit document a.
So that makes my cases different than
the ones I wrote down on my notes. Sorry.
OK.
So if I insert
a line at line i,
I might as well make it match
b j. There's no reason not to.
Right? I might as well kill off
one element of b while I'm at it.
Yeah? So if I do that,
what ends up happening?
Well, I still have to match line i. I've
just kind of moved it lower in my file.
But I've, in essence,
killed one line in file b
by making it match this
new line that I inserted.
In my notes, because I thought I could edit b, I said, OK, I can just
delete the line in b instead. And somehow, logically, that's a lot easier to
think about. But these are
exactly dual to one another.
So in that case, I have xij.
Well, I still have to deal with ai. I haven't
gotten rid of it. But I've matched line j.
So I paid $1 for
inserting a line.
And now I have that, because I've
gotten rid of a line in the other file.
If I stopped here, by the
way, I would have edit distance.
But unfortunately for me, I
have one additional case, which
is mild irritant, as they say,
which is that I can swap.
So if I have a,
now you have to be a little bit careful, because
I'm swapping. So if the next guy in a equals b,
the current guy in b,
and the current guy in a
equals the next guy in b,
well, now I can swap this guy and kill off two lines in
my files while I'm at it. So in this case, I get that xij.
Doesn't cost me anything.
And I killed off two things.
So
that's the recursive. So if I were to write this out on my homework, what
should I do? Well, I shouldn't. I mean, probably if you use this error
notation, I don't think it would be a big deal. But really, you should add
a line at the bottom saying that I can choose to do any of these things.
So really, my recursive
call is xij gets
the min of all of these 1, 2, 3, 4
expressions that I've written here.
OK.
What if you have the first condition but not the second one?
What if I have the first condition but not the second one? Ah,
so
that's a great question. Yeah, so the question was like, OK,
well, what if I can match the next line but not the current one?
Well, there's two different things you could do. You could either make
another case for that. That's perfectly fine. In fact, you could do that. You
could do that I match the second condition, not the first one. Whatever,
you can just enumerate as many things you want as long as they're all true.
And there's a constant number.
Alternatively, you convince yourself that
that actually is unnecessary here because
a different, so
that's like swapping.
But then one of those two lines is still a mismatch. So
you're going to have to delete something in the next step.
So you might as well just delete
first rather than swap and then delete.
And so that's why that
case isn't necessary.
Yeah?
Exactly.
Exactly. So if you swapped and you killed a line, then in
effect, I think it's a combination of case 1 and case 2 here.
If you kind of expand your recursion out. But if you're having trouble
convincing yourself of that, that's fine. Just add a case here.
Yeah?
Any other questions? I'm going to ask quickly
because this problem makes me nervous.
Sure, yeah. OK, in the worst case, if we've done
something wrong, you can certainly add another case here.
I'll think about it at home.
OK, so since I've managed to pontificate
too long, let's keep moving here.
Oh,
yeah, the problem
might have been.
So if you make the swap and
match one of them and not the other,
then that's not OK.
Yeah, because at the end of the day, the
files have to agree. Like, you have to match
B to A. Swap and delete is cheaper than doing two deletes and two inserts.
No, no, no, but the swap and delete is illegal because you have to use
both lines. That's a condition in the problem. Oh, I'm sorry. That's a
better answer. So Jason points out that if I swap thing, I can't delete it
because of the way the problem is written. So that effectively
removes this case. Otherwise, I think, I guess Eric is.
Ah, sorry. I've managed to totally
botch this, which is totally unsurprising.
Yeah, so I think the problem also states
that if you swap, the swap has to be useful.
And that's why this additional case
that Eric is asking about where you swap
and then you match one line
but not the other is unnecessary.
I might be able to relax that by just adding a case here. But
since the problem doesn't ask it, I'm not going to think about it.
OK, great.
So under all the assumptions of this problem that I didn't
read but are very important to solving this problem correctly,
I believe we really have written
down all of our cases here.
OK, so let's continue
with our sort bot paradigm.
So now we have all
of our recursion.
The topological order here
is a little bit trickier
than normal because now you've
got a two -dimensional array.
But it follows a pattern that's pretty
typical here, which is that xij only depends
on other xijs with higher
i plus j. So I think about
my graph of subproblems.
If I wrote this in a 2D matrix, it always
kind of points down and to the right maybe,
which is what's making it acyclic. This is a very typical pattern
in these sort of two -dimensional dynamic programming problems.
All right, so let's see here.
Sort bot, so we need our base case.
This isn't too bad because essentially when you have boring
documents, they're very easy to match to one another.
So in particular,
for any i,
if I'm at line n plus 1, in other words, I
have a blank document that I'm matching to
a document i, well,
how much work do I have to do?
You'd be a little bit careful. This is where the suffix version of this
problem is a little bit more annoying than the prefix one, however I managed
to swap those backward again.
That in particular, the remaining number
of lines looks like n plus 1 minus i,
which
is different than in the problem, it's just i
because they're working in the other direction,
in the solution rather.
And similarly, you need a second
case for those two here. So you have x
n plus 1 j is going to be
n plus 1 minus j.
Cool.
OK,
so
we're going to continue
with sort bot here.
So what is our original
case by definition?
Is x 1 1 or 0 0,
depending on how you index.
And then finally,
what's our runtime?
Well, let's see,
there's n plus 1
squared subproblems.
And of course, that's
equal to order n squared.
The subproblems are just
a constant amount of work.
So they're each
with
constant work.
So our entire runtime
is order n squared.
And hopefully, by watching me be confused in front of you and think
through this problem, you too will see how the problem solving procedure
can happen in your
own disorganized brain.
OK, so that concludes our
treatment of this problem here.
That, I think, is the hardest one. So the other
two, thankfully, are much easier to think about,
I thought.
But I never liked that at distance. I remember seeing
that in undergrad algorithms, getting confused.
OK, so the next problem,
problem three here,
deals with Saggy Mimson.
And she has a bunch of blocks.
And she wants to stack them on
top of each other, as one does. And
as a young structural engineer,
she has a few criteria on her problem.
Let me go to the right
page in my notes here.
But it doesn't really matter, because she's happy
to rotate her cubes any way that she pleases.
There's a key detail, which I did
remember to actually read in this problem,
which is that she
has at least three of
each type.
Where type here means that I can permute these three numbers any
way that I want, because that's the same as just rotating a block.
But any time she has one
block, that's like 1 by 2 by 3,
she has at least two
more in her bag. OK?
Oh, 1 times 2 times 3 is equal
to 6. Thank you, Apple Watch.
OK, so that's odd. So she can orient her block any way that she
wants, meaning she can rotate it in any fashion that she'd like.
And so what we're trying
to do, what we want,
is
the max height
where she's stacking
her n blocks.
I suppose I should
say their n blocks.
So she wants the max height that she can
achieve. But just to be kind of annoying,
or because, again, she's very concerned with
structural stability. She lives in an earthquake zone.
She would like, with the condition
that each block is strictly supported
on the block beneath it.
So in other words,
if this is the base
of one block, then the next block that's stacked on top of
it has to be strictly contained within the block below it.
So the problem makes
sense. Have I omitted any
critical details? I don't think I have
this time. This one's a little easier.
So you can rotate that multiple to 90? Oh, yeah. And she can't do anything
crazy. She can't do a weird balance it on its edge kind of thing, which
is, Eric is absolutely right, could actually give her a taller tower than
you could get if you're only allowed to rotate blocks 90 degrees. I don't
think the problem states that explicitly, but this isn't
a trigonometry class. So I think we're in good shape.
OK, right. So that's
our basic problem here.
This is one of these problems that, like, it's going
to be a dynamic programming problem. But again,
similar to many of the things that we saw
in lecture, it's not totally obvious how,
right? Because somehow,
she has this big disorganized
bag of blocks. You could imagine
a universe where there's 2 to the n
different things she could do, right? For every single block, she could
decide whether or not to put it in her stack. And then she has to do a bunch
of other work to verify whether she can stack them
while supporting the strict support condition or not.
So initially, that
seems kind of annoying.
So what we have to do, which again is
pretty common to a lot of these problems,
is place some order on it. I mean that both in the entropy
sense and also, like, literally, we're going to order stuff.
And in particular, we'll see that this problem has a lot in common
with that longest common subsequence problem that we saw in lecture,
increasing subsequence.
Sorry.
Right.
So here's some observations
about our problem
which are going to help.
First of all,
when we stack our blocks,
we might as well always align the shorter side of the block
on top to the shorter side of the block underneath it.
Right?
Let
me draw a picture
of what I mean.
So let's say I have a really block
whose base kind of looks like that.
And then another block,
which is also rectangular,
that I sit on top
of it like that.
Then notice I could, so in this case, the shorter edge of one block is
aligned to the longer edge of the other. Notice I could rotate it 90 degrees,
and it still supports on one
another. So there's never a case,
you can convince yourself
with just a few inequalities,
where I don't kind of always put the long side parallel to the long side
of the guy underneath it and the short side parallel to the short guy
underneath it. Does
that make sense?
Cool.
So that's observation one.
Observation two. Can
I ever, like let's say
that Maggie actually, sorry,
Saggy actually had not
just three blocks of
a type, but like 25.
So she just like
has hella blocks.
Right? My
question is, does it matter?
The answer is no, because
this word here
is really critical,
which is that there's strict support.
So your block only has so many faces.
Right? And in fact,
by observation one,
really all that matters is which
of the three types of
faces is sitting on top.
Because we can
just always rotate.
So there's three
configurations of every block.
So at most,
can any one configuration appear more than one
time? No, because of the strict support condition.
Right? Otherwise, the rectangles would match
up, and that's against the rules. Yeah?
So in particular,
oops. The number after two is,
the number after one is two,
which looks like that.
OK.
Right. So in particular,
there are only
three orientations.
Right? This is just which of the three edges of the block is the one that's
going away from the floor, the normal to the ground. And moreover, each
can appear
less than or equal to one time.
That's good, because it
limits the size of our problem.
And finally,
oops.
Well, I collapsed
two of the cases in my notes
into one case here. But that's OK.
And in fact, notice that the problem tells us that
she has at least three of each type. So in a sense,
if the problem, if you observe one of a block, you might as well just throw
away the rest. Because you know that you can use it at most three times,
and she has three of that block. We can't use it more than
three times. So in a sense, that's just surplus information.
OK.
Right. So this allows us to put a little bit of order here.
Because notice that when I look at the stack of blocks here,
what do we know? If I look
at the length of the long side
and the length of the short side
in the plane of the ground,
those numbers have to decrease
on every level of my block.
Right? They can never increase. That's what the strict support condition
says. So combined with observation one, actually even without observation
one,
which is good news.
Right? So this is what's going to allow us to impose order
on our problem, namely that we can sort by the edge lengths,
because we know that we
have this support condition.
OK. So let's fill in some
details of our algorithm.
OK.
So right.
So originally, already we can see that our list of blocks is kind of
useless, because the width, length, and height values are sorted in ways that
don't matter.
Moreover, if we have more than three of a
given block, that's somehow not super useful.
So instead of that,
without loss of generality, let's assume, so w, l,
o, g here. We can always take our block and assume,
I'm going to do this slightly
different from my notes, that the width
is less than or
equal to the height.
Is less than or equal to the
length. OK. So every block,
if this isn't the case, I could go down my array of blocks and
sort. And sorting a list of three numbers is constant time.
OK.
Right.
So what does this allow me to do? Well, I'm going to say that a block type
actually is an ordered set, where the third number is going to be the axis
that points up.
And the reason to do that is that we know that we can
never use that more than once for any type of a block.
Yeah. So now,
I'm going to make
a new list of blocks
with
a capital B, because
I like blocks.
And it's going to look like
the following. So if width,
so if w is less than
h is less than l,
then I'm going to take
every block and duplicate it
three times.
Notice that I might end up with a list with like
nine times of every block, but we'll fix that later.
Right. And it's going to
look like the following,
which is that, OK,
I'm going to have w, i, h, i, l, i. This is like describing a way to
stack my block, right? Because it's saying, this is the short side,
this is the long side,
this is the vertical side.
Yeah.
And there are three cases where any one of these guys
can be the vertical side. So there's one, let's say that
the h is the vertical side, then w
has to go before l. So it would be w, i,
l, i,
h, i.
And a third one, where
the third guy is w,
h is less than l. So it
would be h, i, l, i, w, i.
And those are all the
different ways that I can sort
of orient these blocks in my stacking, assuming that
I impose condition one for convenience here. OK.
I'm going to make a new list of blocks where I take every block in my
original set and I just duplicate it three times this way after I sort its
coordinates.
And now, well, what do I need to do? Well, for one thing, this thing may
have too many blocks. I might have a block that's repeated more than one
time, and I know
I can't do that.
And moreover, it's going to be convenient to have this
sorted because I got to stack these guys eventually.
Yeah.
So I'm going to sort
that list.
And I want to do it, I can never
say this word, lexicographically,
meaning that
I'm going to sort on the first coordinate,
and then the second, and the third,
lexicographically.
Notice this length
is 3n if I had n
blocks to start with.
So this entire thing
takes order n log
n time, which is
important to account for.
And then I can
remove duplicates.
What's going on in this thing?
OK. So now, finally,
we can do our sort bot.
And I might do s and r and t and then allow you guys to
think about the rest because, as usual, I'm talking too much.
OK. So now,
this is starting to look like a subsequence problem because, essentially,
when I stack my blocks, if I use this block here, again, if I'm stacking
from my tower from the top down,
all the blocks that can sit underneath this one have to be
farther to the right in my array because of the way that I sorted.
Now, that doesn't mean that I can put anything on the right underneath this
guy. But it does mean that I know nothing to the left can go underneath
this guy. That's the
way to think about it.
OK. So here's going
to be sort bot. So s,
what I'm going to say is that xi here is
equal to the maximum height of my tower.
And so, to get a little bit of inspiration from
our subsequence problem that we've already seen,
I'm going to force myself to use
block i. We'll see that's convenient.
i and possibly,
just
for fun, maybe we'll do the prefix
version of this problem this time.
So now,
I can use any of
the previous blocks.
So I can use the first i blocks to make a tower. But I'm forced to use
block i. By the way, from now on, when I use indices, it's into this sorted
array.
OK.
So this is a problem. Obviously, if I could solve for x, I would be done
because I could get the maximum height by just iterating over all the x's
and choosing the
biggest possible
value here. And the question
is, how do I do this recursively?
OK. So here's our
recursive step.
So
let's say that I use block i.
Well, because
we know we have to.
So in particular,
we have a now I'm seeing why
they didn't use this notation
in their answer. But that's OK.
Let's use another letter to
refer to the third coordinate.
Yeah. Let's say vi is always the third coordinate. So if I were to use wh
and l, and I'm afraid if I reuse them after sorting, it's going to confuse
people.
So vi
is the third
coordinate of the is
element of my sorted array.
That's fine. OK.
Right. So what is my height? If I use
xi here, well, I get some height from vi.
And in addition to that, I get
whatever I stack underneath that guy.
So in particular, I get that xi. Well, I get the
height of the block that I just decided to use.
And now,
what are all my cases?
Well, I could decide to do nothing else, like just
not use any other blocks. That gives me a height of 0.
Here,
well, let's see here.
I could use the x's, but I have to be
careful that I can actually stack them.
So in particular,
well,
I need,
yeah, I
can take an xj value, but I got to be
careful that I can stack it underneath.
So in particular,
what
do we know? Well, I can do
anything from 1 to i minus 1,
right? Because that's sort
of the definition of xi.
But in particular,
I can stack it on top.
So one easy way to do this
is I iterate through the
first i minus 1 elements of my array, and I just check my stacking condition
for every single one of them relative to block j. So in other words,
that the width and the height, or rather the first and the
second coordinate satisfy the strict inequalities that I need.
I'm phrasing this sentence
neutrally because I forget whether
this is increasing or decreasing.
But in any event,
so what do I do? I check all of the blocks that I could possibly stack
from the index of the array perspective. I make sure that I could actually
stack them thanks to the size of the current
block that I just decided to add to my stack.
And I move recursively.
OK.
Right, so
this is great because now we're in exactly the recursive scenario we wanted
to be in, right? Because xi only depends on xj where j is smaller than i.
And that is exactly our
topological ordering that we need.
If you do that on your homework,
you get minus n for large N.
OK.
Similarly, what's our base case?
Well,
obviously,
if I only have one block,
I might as well use it.
Yeah. So in that case, we have x1 is equal
to, I guess, in our notation here, like that.
Our original one,
we have to do it a little bit careful
because of the way that I've defined x.
Because x assumes that
I've used a particular block,
right? So I have to say, well, I might not have actually
chosen the very last block as the one I want to keep.
So I have to iterate.
And then
our final thing to
do is the runtime,
t.
This one is mildly trickier than the previous runtimes
that we've done so far in our example problem.
In particular,
how many subproblems are there?
Well, there's n subproblems.
Or I'll say order n
because I'm always off by 1.
Order n work
per subproblem.
So at the end of the day,
my algorithm
is going to be order
n squared times.
And of course, again, I guess I promised it and then I
didn't actually do it. To actually implement this algorithm,
there's sort of two different
ways to do it. I could
write a recursive
call plus a table.
The table is maybe initialized to a bunch of nans. And then I implement this
function recursively. But before I do that, I say, if the table does not
equal nan, just return the
value in the table and otherwise
call this recursion.
Or I could just have
a for loop from 1 to n
and build up the table one element at a time. And both
of those are exactly the same from a runtime perspective.
OK, so I think I've managed to botch that much more than my notes or the
written solution. But the problem itself is actually pretty straightforward.
So if you guys read through the answer on some of the, I think actually
the hard parts of this problem were not the dynamic programming. It was all
the observations you need to get there. So
that's why I spent a little more time there.
OK, so as usual, I haven't left myself enough time for the last problem.
But we have a few minutes. And that'll be sufficient to set up the parts.
I actually found the last problem to be easier, even though
it technically is sort of two dynamic programs in one.
Somehow I think the
logic is a little easier.
OK,
so.
I think this is the backboard. Yeah, I was just realizing
that this room doesn't work the same way as the other one.
Yeah, this is embarrassing. I spent
all day thinking about topology. And
it's like a classic kind
of problem in that universe.
OK, well, we'll just erase one board at a time. And I'll try not to write
three feet wide this time. Oh, this is probably the one board I shouldn't
use.
I don't think I
like this classroom.
OK, so.
Right, and our final problem,
we're given an n by n grid.
And on our n by n grid,
Princess Apple,
Banana,
Plum. Princess Plum.
Right, so here's our basic
setup. There's a big grid of stuff.
Or maybe a small grid, because
I don't feel like drawing.
And every grid square can have one of
three things. We can have a mushroom.
We can have a tree.
Or it can have nothing at all.
And our princess starts here.
And she wants
to go there.
And moreover, there's a couple of things that are
worth noting here. So first of all, her path is quick,
meaning
that she can only traverse
2n minus 1 grid squares
to
get from one
corner to the other.
And apparently,
she's very into mushrooms. And she'd like to accumulate as
many as possible along her path. That's the basic setup here.
So she wants to get
from the upper left
to the lower right.
And in order to do so, she
wants to take a quick path.
So her main priority
is to be efficient.
But among the
different quick paths,
she wants to pick up
a lot of mushrooms.
It's understandable.
And
not walk through trees. Thank you. So maybe there's some grid squares
that are marked with a tree, meaning that you just can't go there.
That's a tree.
OK, right, so that's our basic setup here. But the problem is, it takes a
bit of a twist. It's not saying just compute the shortest path, which would
be very much like the last
kind of unit. And 6 ,006.
But rather,
the question is, what
is the number of paths
that she can take from
one side to the other?
And what is the maximum
number of mushrooms
is roughly the question asking, at least what I remember from reading it
last night. The number of paths that maximize same number. That's right. So
she has to take the most number of mushrooms she can. But there may be
more than one path that gets you there that is quick, that satisfies this
condition,
in which case she wants the count of the total number of ways
she could get from one corner to the other. Why, you might ask?
Why not?
OK, so right.
So for instance, maybe
there's a mushroom here.
Now there's a quick path that gets her there and collects one mushroom.
So there's exactly one. But maybe if there's a mushroom there,
well, initially, it feels like maybe she
could get two mushrooms. She could go there,
go up, pick up the second
mushroom, and get back.
But we're going to see that this quick
condition actually doesn't allow you to do that.
So in fact, it'll turn out that quick paths can only collect one
mushroom in this 3 by 3 case. So there's at least two different paths.
Well, there's one, two,
three different ways that she could
collect one mushroom and have a quick path.
So the first thing to notice,
your structure is
a little bit sneaky
by defining quick paths basically
by giving her no slack at all.
And
here's the basic observation.
Notice that in order to get from the upper left to the bottom
right, she's going to have to go down and to the right.
Plausibly, she could also go up.
She could try and go around a tree.
But only plausibly.
And in particular, the question is,
how many times does she have to go down,
and how many times does
she have to go to the right?
Well, she has to get to
the bottom of the grid.
So she's on grid
square number 1.
She has to go down,
in this case, at least two more
times. So in general, n minus 1 times.
She has to go to the right,
n minus 1 times.
So what does that mean? She
has to make 2n minus 2 moves.
And that's a lower bound. So if she goes up, she's going to
have to go down again. So it's only going to make it bigger.
So at the very least, she
has to do 2n minus 2 moves.
You know, down and right to get
from the upper left to the lower right.
How
many squares does she touch when she's doing that? Well, this is a fence
post problem. So she made 2n minus 2 moves, and she had a place where she
started.
That
implies that just by moving down and to
the right, she makes 2n minus 1 squares.
She touches,
rather.
So can she ever move up?
No. Can she ever
move to the left? No.
And that, basically, is all you need to solve this problem. The rest of it's
actually pretty easy. So the basic observation here is she can only move
down and to the right. Because if she moved up or to the left, her
path would no longer be called quick. And that would be a problem.
Moreover, every path that moves
down and to the right is a quick path,
assuming she reaches her
target and doesn't hit a tree.
So that's the basic observation. And notice that that already basically
suggests it's screaming out to you. How did you do dynamic programming?
Because literally,
you have a table
looking at you on the blackboard right now. And you
have an ordering down and to the right that is acyclic.
Yeah?
OK. Have I slammed on the board enough times? The first time I taught at
Stanford, I got negative course feedback that I had too much coffee and was
slamming on the board
a lot, apparently.
I watched the video later.
And indeed, that was not wrong.
OK.
So right.
So we're going to call k.
This is going to be the max
mushrooms
she can get going on the entire path from the upper left to the lower
right. So we want to know the number of quick paths that can achieve this
number, k.
OK. So let's do sort by.
Really fast,
because I've got four minutes.
Actually, a tiny bit more than
that, because we started late.
OK.
Now,
the kind of annoyance here is that there's
two different numbers that we don't know.
One of them is k, and the other is the number of paths. The problem didn't
tell you how many mushrooms she can pick up. It does tell you that there's
some path to get from the upper left to the bottom
right, that there's not just a row of trees somewhere,
which I feel on my
commute sometimes.
But
it doesn't tell you the number
that she has to accomplish.
Actually, that's kind of annoying. So maybe the first thing that we do is
just compute k, like the maximum number of mushrooms that she can collect
on any quick path.
And then we go back and compute that other count. Yeah, that would be
one problem solving approach that we could think about a little bit.
So in particular, let's define
our kij
to be equal to. Well, we can generalize our problem slightly and say,
what is the number of mushrooms that I can get on any kind of rectangle
embedded inside
of my full problem?
So in other words,
this is the max
number of mushrooms,
or m's for short,
on a quick
path
to ij. So in other words, she always starts in the
upper left, but now she stops at any other grid cell.
OK.
So I'm low on time.
No, I'm going to do this the way I want to do
this. No. So we're just going to think about k.
So the question is, could we compute just this
value k, which certainly seems convenient?
Like Princess Plum, really, she might as well know her enemy. She might
as well know the number of mushrooms she's targeting if she can get it.
So
how could we do
this recursively?
Well, she has to get
to position ij.
And from our argument up there,
she has to get there by either
coming from up or to the left,
the way we've chosen to
write down this problem.
So
what are our different cases?
Well, first of all,
if there's a tree,
you can't do a damn thing. She shouldn't even be able to get there. And
for convenience, we're going to find, you could argue that it's 0. We're
going to mark this with a special number, and we'll
see that that makes our notation a little convenient.
So 1 is if there exists a tree,
then we're going to say kij is minus infinity. Again, there's a
philosophical question there. Does she get minus infinity mushrooms if she is
standing on top of a tree? I don't know, because she shouldn't stand on
top of a tree. But at least it's going to let us know that something went
wrong in this grid square in
the other parts of our recursion.
OK.
And otherwise,
well, what are our different
cases here?
Well,
she always picks up a mushroom if it's
there. She might as well. She's maximizing.
In fact, I think the problem even says that she's
really new mushrooms. She collects them automatically.
So what do we get?
I'll use unnecessarily fancy notation. This is
an indicator of whether there exists a mushroom
at
position ij.
Right?
Meaning this is a 1 if there
is, and there's a 0 if there's not.
Sometimes this is indicated with a 1
with a little subscript, but whatever.
And in addition to that, she might have picked up mushrooms along paths.
And we know that her path to position ij either came from up or to the left.
Right? So in other
words, we know
that she could have gotten the max from any path
ending above her or any path to the left of her.
So that's ki minus 1j,
which I guess is to the left,
and ki j minus 1, like that.
And this can be used to fill
in our whole table of k values.
In fact, since I'm low on
time, I'll let you do the t bot
for the remainder of this problem. Right?
Essentially, I think the key observation is this one.
Right? Obviously, when she starts in the upper left, zero mushrooms
because she's not standing on top of one. The problem says that.
And this allows us to
fill in our whole table k.
So in particular, this gives us our enemy now. We now know how many mushrooms
she should have at every step of her journey. In fact, it tells us a
tiny bit more than that.
Right? Because it says, if I'm at this grid square,
at this particular grid square during my path,
I should have this many mushrooms.
If I didn't, then something went wrong.
Yeah?
So the way that the solution is written, they do two pieces of the recursion
at once. You actually could have just solved for this k matrix first and
then gone back and done the
second half of this problem.
And those are exactly the same.
Yeah? And when I was writing my solution, this is the way I thought about
it because somehow I kind of thought, like, she might as well know how many
mushrooms she wants to collect before she starts
counting paths. That's like a secondary question.
And so this is one way to do it. So
in our remaining negative two minutes,
let's think about the recursion for computing.
Remember that we want to know the number of paths
needed to collect
that many mushrooms,
the maximum number of mushrooms.
Please let there not be a
whole lot of stuff on this board.
Ah, there's not any stuff on
this board. That's great. OK.
So in particular,
now I'm going to define a second thing that I also am going
to do dynamic programming on. Yeah? I'm going to say that xij
is equal to, and I'm going to
make kind of a sneaky definition.
Here, which is the
number of quick paths
that end at ij with,
now let's anticipate
our problem a little bit.
So at the end of the day, we're going to do like x of n comma
n because she wants to end up all the way down to the right.
And how many mushrooms does she want to have now that we
know k? She wants to have k of n comma n mushrooms. Along
the way,
it would be kind of ambitious if she wanted to
have k of n comma n mushrooms the entire path.
But it would be slightly less ambitious to have k of ij mushrooms because
somehow that's exactly what we just constructed in the previous thing was
path.
So well,
the last guy looks like max. Now we're going to expect to see some
plus signs here because we're like adding up how many paths we have.
And now let's come up with our recursive rule
for this array x, and then we'll call it a day.
So in particular,
go ahead. One,
if there's a tree,
how many paths are there?
There are no paths because I
can't get there. Yeah? So then ij
equals 0.
OK? Otherwise,
there ain't a tree.
And now I have to
be a little careful.
So I'm going to write this
like a little piece of code.
You could have written this as a giant max
instead and a bunch of cases and whatever.
So let's think about it like a piece of code. So initially, I think
there are no paths that get me k, ij, mushrooms. That's perfectly fine.
And remember, we're going to keep applying the same piece of
logic, which is that a path can only come from to the left and up.
And let's think
about those two cases.
And by the way, we're going to use chi to equal this
chi of stuff that we had in the previous expression.
So chi is 1 if there's a mushroom
at this place and 0 if there is not.
OK.
So my path can come
from the left or up.
I know that it can't come from up if the number of mushrooms that I got
from up plus potentially the one that I got here doesn't align with the
number of mushrooms that I should have by the
k, ij standard that I have set for myself.
Yeah? So if I want to
write that out in code,
the way I do that is I say if k of,
so let's say I look to the left first.
This is like look to your left,
look to your right. One of you will
pass this exam kind of scenario.
And I potentially add a mushroom at
my current position if there is one.
If that is equal to k, ij, well, what does that mean? That means that paths
that went to the left were able to collect the number of mushrooms I need
to get to the position I am now.
So now I can add what?
Well, all of the different
ways. Maybe I'll do a plus equals
x of i minus 1j,
right? Because any path that got to the previous guy and collected the
right number of mushrooms can now reach me and get the right number of
mushrooms.
And similarly, I can look up and do exactly the same logic.
So if k of ij minus 1 plus this number is equal to k, ij,
then x,
ij
gets an additional
number of paths like that.
And now I do think it's worth spending
8 seconds thinking about our base cases.
Here, because initially when I first saw this, I panicked a little bit
because it kind of looks like this would just end up giving you a bunch of
zeros,
right? Because I'm just adding values of x's to
themselves. I don't have a 1 plus anything anywhere,
which is kind of weird
if you think about it.
So all of the reason why the positive numbers appear in this
problem is from the base case, which is kind of cool, I think.
I think one of these things where if you anticipated a problem, then it's
cool. And if you didn't anticipate the problem to begin with, you just
wrote down these formulas, you probably
wouldn't even think that it's interesting.
But in any event,
what is our base case? So
we'll do the B in sort bot.
So first of all,
what
is k of 1, 1? Remember, that's the number of mushrooms you
can collect by starting at the left square and going nowhere.
And
that's 0 because the problem says
there's no mushrooms in the upper left.
What's x of 1, 1? Well, this is the number of
paths from 1, 1 to itself that collect 0 mushrooms.
So that's 1.
And I think that the rest of the sort bot table here isn't terribly
difficult to fill in. So notice that in a kind of a funny way, all of these
recursive steps are just adding
1 to itself a bunch of times.
But of course, the way you do that, the reason why you get a number that's
interesting is because of all these if statements and the fact that you
can add two different pluses
coming from two different sources.
So I actually do encourage you guys to look at the code in the problem
solution because I think it's a nice example of thinking this recursive
formula and then unrolling
it into iterating over a table.
And that's a useful skill that I intended to do
today and then didn't actually do very carefully.
But with that, as usual, we've gone over time here.
So we'll call it for the day. And I will see you guys
when I see you guys.
All right.